Finding Aid for George Owen Squier Papers, 1883-1934
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
George Owen Squier papers 1883-1934
Squier, George Owen, 1865-1934.
2 oversize folders
7 linear feet
8674 Aa 2; UAm; Ac
Major general in the U.S. Army, physicist, and inventor. Correspondence, personal account books, reports, military orders, student notebooks (U.S. Military Academy and Johns Hopkins University), notes and other material largely related to his scientific interests, particularly in telegraphy and trans-oceanic cables; also diaries kept while a West Point cadet, one of which contains a family history and autobiography; Ph.D. thesis in physics from Johns Hopkins University; and photographs.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was the gift of Mrs. Lorena Babcock (donor no. 2067 ) and came to the library in 1945.
The collection is open to research.
George Owen Squier was born in Dryden, Michigan on March 21, 1865. He entered the army as a second lieutenant of artillery following his graduation from West Point Military Academy in 1887. He was then stationed at Fort McHenry, Md., during which time he studied physics, chemistry, and mathematics at Johns Hopkins University, receiving his Ph.D. in 1893. From 1894 to 1895, he attended the Artillery School at Fort Monroe, Virginia, and from November 1895 to April 1898, he was an instructor in the school.
From 1900 to 1902, Squier was commander of the US cable-ship Burnside which laid submarine cables in the Philippine archipelago. He next superintended the construction of telegraph lines in the Philippine Islands. During the coming years, Squier advanced in rank and would be stationed at San Francisco, Fort Leavenworth, and Washington DC. In 1911-1912, he became military attaché at the US embassy in London. The army provided Squier with many opportunities for study and research in areas of interest to him. As a scientist, he conducted research on such topics as the electrochemical effects due to magnetization; the sine wave systems of telegraphy and ocean cabling, the absorption of electro-magnetic waves by living vegetable organisms, among others. His inventions were primarily in the area of telephony: wireless, multiple, and long-distance. He was also inventor of the monophone for broadcasting over telephone wires.
George O. Squier died March 24, 1934
The George Owen Squier papers include correspondence, personal account books, reports, military orders, student notebooks (U.S. Military Academy and Johns Hopkins University), notes and other material largely related to his scientific interests, particularly in telegraphy and trans-oceanic cables; diaries kept while a West Point cadet, one of which contains a family history and autobiography; Squier's Ph.D. thesis in physics from Johns Hopkins University; and photographs.
The Squier collection has been arranged into the following series: Correspondence; Inventions and Research; Military Career; Miscellaneous / Personal; and Education (West Point and Johns Hopkins).
Subjects:
Inventions.; Johns Hopkins University.; Lapeer County (Mich.); Physicists--United States.; Radio.; Scientists--United States.; Voyages and travels.; United States. Army.; United States Military Academy.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Boats.; Camps.; Communication devices--1921-1930.; Dryden (Mich.)--Parks.; Dryden Community Park (Dryden, Mich.); Dwellings.; Inventions.; Parks--Michigan--Dryden.; Soldiers--American.; Squier, George Owen, 1865-1934.; Squier family.; United States. Army. Signal Corps.; Vermont--1921-1930.
Contributors:
Angell, James Rowland, 1869-1949.; Baker, Newton Diehl, 1871-1937.; Beard, Daniel Carter, 1850-1941.; Chapin, Roy D. (Roy Dikeman), 1880-1936.; Coffin, Howard Earle, 1873-1937.; Couzens, James, 1872-1936.; Cramton, Louis C. (Louis Convers), b. 1875.; Forrestal, James, 1872-1936.; House, Edward Mandell, 1858-1938.; Kennely, Arthur Edwin, 1861-1939.; Lansing, Robert, 1864-1928.; Wainwright, Jonathan Mayhew, 1883-1953.; Wright, Orville, 1871-1948.; Yerkes, Robert Mearns, 1876-1956.
Genre Terms:
Account books.; Albums.; Diaries.; Photographs.; Tintypes.
- Correspondence
  - 1896-1919, 33 folders (Box 1)
  - 1920-June 1922, 26 folders (Box 2)
  - July 1922-1930, 23 folders (Box 3)
  - 1933-1934 1944-1945 (Box 3)
  - Undated (Box 3)
- Inventions and research
  - Report upon the International Electrical Congress at Chicago 1893 (Box 4)
    (also include specification on hand-drawn copper wire)
  - Report: "Some tests of the magnetic qualities of gun steel" April 1894 (Box 4)
  - Correspondence and material concerning submarine cable telegraphs and other inventions 1900, 1913 (Box 4)
    (formerly in binder)
  - Research studies and reports on various inventions, 4 folders (Box 4)
  - Miscellaneous reports and notes (Box 4)
  - Miscellaneous material concerning Squier's inventions, 2 folders (Box 4)
  - Blueprints of Squier's inventions (Box 4)
  - Squier's wireless system, 2 folders (Box 4)
  - Notes and draft of manuscript for "The alternating current for cable telegraphy", 4 folders (Box 4)
  - Miscellaneous reports (Box 4)
  - Newspaper clippings (Box 4)
  - Miscellanea (Box 4)
  - Printed articles by GOS; patent specifications; and other publications (Box 4)
  - Writings on military arts and studies 1892-1893 (Box 4)
    (titles include "Recent researches in electricity and magnetism" and "Journal of the U.S. Artillery -- discussion of Lieut. Parkhurst's article")
  - Scrapbook of letters 1904-1905 mainly acknowledgements to the receipt of GOS's paper on the absorption of electromagnetic waves by living vegetable organisms (Box 4)
- Military career
  - Record book containing personal orders and letters 1891-1892 (Box 5)
  - Record book containing personal orders and letters 1895 (Box 5)
    (include many letters from Albert C. Crehore)
  - Artillery lectures notes (Fort Monroe, Va.) 1897 (Box 5)
  - Notebook with jottings from trip to London with Albert C. Crehore 1897 (Box 5)
  - Diary of trip to London and Paris 1897 (Box 5)
    (include comments on discussion with British scientists)
  - Account book 1893-1906 (Box 5)
  - Scrapbook containing clippings and engineering notes 1900 (Box 5)
  - Personal Report -- Officers 1923 (Box 5)
  - Special orders 1918-1923 (Box 5)
- Miscellaneous / Personal
  - Biographical information (Box 5)
    (include passport)
  - Notebook containing letters to sister and cousins written from Europe 1887 (Box 5)
  - Pictorial family register (Box 5)
    (include some photographic portraits and genealogical information about family members)
  - Photographs
    - Portraits, group photos (Box 5)
      (see also oversize folder)
    - Inventions; miscellaneous (Box 5)
- Education (West Point and Johns Hopkins)
  - West Point Military Academy
    - Conduct reports 1883-1887 (Box 6)
    - Literary notebook kept while attending West Point 1883-1884 also contains autobiography (Box 6)
    - Literary notebook kept while attending West Point 1885-1886 (Box 6)
    - Expense book 1883 (Box 6)
    - Course notebook in Mechanics 1885 (Box 6)
    - Course papers (Box 6)
  - Johns Hopkins University / Artillery School, Fort Monroe, Va.
    - Student notebooks 1890-1894 (Box 6)
    - Student notebooks 1890-1894 (Box 7)
    - Thesis entitled "A dissertation on electro-chemical effects due to magnetization" 1892 (Box 7)
Selective Index to Correspondents
This index lists some of the more significant corespondents in the chronologically arranged portion of the Correspondence series. It cites the correspondent and the date(s) of correspondence.
Angell, James Rowland, 1869-1949.
October 22, 1919, June 11, 1922
Baker, Newton Diehl, 1871-1937.
November 12, 1918, December 1920, May 2, 1921
Beard, Daniel Carter, 1850-1941.
March 16, 1920
Chapin, Roy D. (Roy Dikeman), 1880-1936.
April 11, 1922
Coffin, Howard Earle, 1873-1937.
February 20, 1922
Couzens, James, 1872-1936.
November 11, 1929
Cramton, Louis C. (Louis Convers), b. 1875.
1919
Forrestal, James, 1872-1936.
January 18, 1945
House, Edward Mandell, 1858-1938.
April 8, 1919
Kennely, Arthur Edwin, 1861-1939.
1915, 1919, 1921
Lansing, Robert, 1864-1928.
May 14, 1923, May 15, 1923
Wainwright, Jonathan Mayhew, 1883-1953.
Date not listed
Wright, Orville, 1871-1948.
February 8, 1919
Yerkes, Robert Mearns, 1876-1956.
February 28, 1920